{
  "reference_number": "4805",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a goal to reach net zero emissions by the second half of the century and the Climate Change Commission advises on the specific target for the Government to set later",
      "answer_index": 11,
      "notes": "The target date should be 2030"
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "Net is not good enough, it has to be zero for each greenhouse gas."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "New forest planting of long lived trees."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "We are talking zero now but will probably need negative carbon soon."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Providing they are stricter ie less emissions."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": "Only if it reduces further the permitted emissions."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Only if it further reduces the emissions."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Remove the economic considerations. We are talking about the survival oif our species. First ensure that then think about economics.\nThe cost is irrelevant when survival is at stake. If you put a cost to it then, by implication, when that economic cost is reached we stop\n\ntrying and just die."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Much sooner rather than later."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Consider this, approximately three trillion trees on this planet are not coping with the emissions we make so planting in the billions\n\nwill not help. We have to cut down our emissions drastically and change the way we survive."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Unless the government is forced to take notice what good will a monitor be?"
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "NZ ETS should be scrapped because we all need to make sacrifices and not just the rich who can buy their way out of changes."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Disagree with economic expertise being needed. We are trying to save our species and we don't need to set a price on that."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "It is the key to saving our species."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Impact on our health and culture is really secondary to our survival. We might have to put up with sub-optimal health in order to\nsurvive."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "No exceptions for any business, commercial or government."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The Paris agreement is a shame on humans. It is unfortunately needed because we are unable to make ourselves do what is\n\nnecessary without others being made to do the same. We have all created this situation and must all respond to trying to mitigate\nsome of it. The government must react more urgently than it is doing at present regardless of what any previous government did to\n\nmake things more difficult now. At present Regional Councils are granting consents which are negating any efforts to mitigate climate\nchange. There should be a moratorium on all consents now. In the Edgecumbe Flood of 2017 I lost my family home of 30 years. The\nCouncil has taken over my property to repair the breached stopbank and reposition a roadway but is negating any works it does by\n\ngranting consents which will produce more green house gas. Don't spend so much time on the bureaucracy that we make the\nsituation worse and are then less able to do something about it."
    }
  ]
}
